LUIS QUINTERO

E-mail: levelezq@gmail.com
https://luiseduve.github.io/
City:
Stockholm, Sweden

SUMMARY

Researcher in machine learning and virtual reality technologies. Experience in the development of bioinspired interactive technologies using techniques from signal processing, data science, computer vision, and human-computer interaction. Interested in designing and evaluating innovative systems that merge digital health sensors with immersive visualization systems to improve health, education, and training. Highly autonomous and seeker of permanent learning, knowledge in project management and agile approaches.

Hardware: Oculus, HTC Vive, Polar, Zephyr, Myo, Emotiv.

Programming: C#, C++, Python.

Platforms/Libraries: Unity, OpenCV, Qt, Scikit-learn.

WORK EXPERIENCE

RESEARCHER - PhD SCHOLAR

June 2019 – Present Stockholm, Sweden

Research area is the intersection between machine learning and immersive technologies.
The problem of interest is how to use data from the interaction with systems for virtual
reality training to identify the skill level of a user and adapt the task in such a way that
improves their learning processes.

VIRTUAL REALITY DEVELOPER

February 2017 - August 2017

Madeira Interactive Technology Institute, Portugal

- Design, and development of a research VR application for HTC-Vive seeking for mental health wellbeing. Using programming of physiological sensors in C# and Unity.
- Contribution in the implementation of calibration tool for low-cost CAVE systems using the Kinect sensor.
- Contribution in a framework for physiologically-adapted interactive systems for health promotion in the elderly population. Implementing a real-time visual scripting in Unity3D.

BIOENGINEERING PROFESSIONAL

April 2015 - January 2017

Colombia's Center for Bioinformatics and Computational Biology (BIOS), Colombia

- Formulation and planning of project's proposals aimed to build customized hardwaresoftware systems for manufacturing plants, using computer vision and data processing algorithms.
- Support in development tasks of a computer vision system used for control quality in an assembly line at a multinational company.
- Development of applications using computer-generated imagery and digital signal processing with hardware devices programming.

EDUCATION

(Current) 2019 - 2024 DOCTORAL DEGREE

PhD in Computer and Systems Sciences

Stockholm University, Stockholm, Sweden.

2017 - 2019 POSTGRADUATE DEGREE

MSc. Health Informatics

Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm, Sweden.

- Design and development of immersive and interactive systems for patients, supporting their empowerment in self-care processes.
- Thesis: "Facilitating Technology-based Mental Health Interventions with Mobile Virtual Reality and Wearable Smartwatches"

2010 - 2015 UNDERGRADUATE DEGREE ELECTRONICS ENGINEER

National University of Colombia, Manizales, Colombia.

Grade Point Average: 4.4

- Award: Best 10% GPA among graduated students.
- **Award:** Top-best results in national undergraduate examination.
- Main topics: Digital and signal processing, hardware programming, control systems.

2009 - 2011 TECHNICAL DEGREE COMPUTER SYSTEMS TECHNICIAN

Unitécnica, Manizales, Colombia.

 Basic principles of computer systems, web development, databases, software setup and hardware maintenance.

PUBLICATIONS

Complete list of publications: https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=RYg PGQAAAAJ

- (2020) Luis Quintero. Research Methodologies when Combining Virtual Reality with Machine Learning: A Brief Scoping Review. *In The 13th PErvasive Technologies Related to Assistive Environments Conference (PETRA'20)*, Corfu, Greece. ACM, 4 pages. https://doi.org/10.1145/3389189.3394093
- (2020) Muñoz JE, Quintero L, Stephens CL and Pope AT. A Psychophysiological Model of Firearms Training in Police Officers: A Virtual Reality Experiment for Biocybernetic Adaptation. Frontiers in Psychology. 11:683. Journal (Open Access) https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2020.00683
- (2019) Luis Quintero, John Muñoz, Panagiotis Papapetrou. Open-Source Physiological Computing Framework using Heart Rate Variability in Mobile Virtual Reality Applications. 2nd International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Virtual Reality (AIVR 2019), San Diego, CA, USA. https://doi.org/10.1109/AIVR46125.2019.00027
- (2019) Luis Quintero, Panagiotis Papapetrou, John Muñoz, Uno Fors. Implementation of Mobile-based Real-time Heart Rate Variability Detection for Personalized Healthcare. Workshop TMDM in IEEE International Conference on Data Mining (ICDM2019), Beijing, China. https://doi.org/10.1109/ICDMW.2019.00123
- (2018) Badia, S. B. i, Quintero, L. V., Cameirao, M. S., Chirico, A., Triberti, S., Cipresso, P., & Gaggioli, A. (2018). *Towards Emotionally-Adaptive Virtual Reality for Mental Health Applications*. IEEE Journal of Biomedical and Health Informatics, 1–1. https://doi.org/10.1109/JBHI.2018.2878846

PROJECTS AND PORTFOLIO

(2020) Excite-O-Meter[Website]

Tool created in Unity that allows integrating human-body signals into interactive applications to quantify and visualize our inner responses during and after immersive experience. The tool uses scientifically validated principles of cardiovascular reactivity to illustrate how the measured levels of excitement are affected during XR experiences.

(2018) EasyBlood [Video]

Mobile Virtual Reality application deployed in Unity. The solution is meant to be used in hospital settings to aid health practitioners to handle children anxiety during blood samples, it uses game-based mechanics to distract the users.

(2018) ArmRehabVR [Website]

Mobile-VR environment with virtual limbs controlled remotely via VRPN protocol. Part of a system to aid rehabilitation of spinal cord injury through EEG monitoring and virtual reality.

(2018) PortalSense [Website]

Founder and product manager of a company that deploys interactive and immersive systems using high-end virtual reality for industry and education.

(2018) BioPhyS [Website]

System to enhance cognitive skills in virtual military training, using sophisticated biofeedback technologies that deliver highly adaptive scenarios aiming at boosting skills in military personnel based on recognition of physiological signals.

- Development of first demo of the adaptive shooting application in Unity.
- Integration of physiological signals with communication protocols (UDP) in Unity.

(2017) 3Dream [Video]

VR tool used to train emotional regulation in psychology. It uses HTC-Vive and wearable devices to estimate user's emotion and create content procedurally accordingly.

• Development of the virtual environment in Unity3D, communication protocols and signal processing of physiological data.

(2017) BL-ENGINE & CAVE SYSTEM [Video]

Support in the development of a software tool designed for an easy creation of physiologically modulated videogames by means of wearable sensors. And one for interaction with Kinect sensor in CAVE systems.

- Design and coding of visual scripting module using Unity3D.
- Implementation of a 3D calibration tool for low-cost VR CAVE systems.

(2015) VILIMBS [Video]

Bio-signal-based interaction with virtual limbs to improve rehabilitation for amputees with phantom limb pain phenomenon.

 Coding the migration from wired EMG device to wireless Myo device. GUI design and coding for ViLimbs application using Ot and C++ libraries.

(2015) VIDEOWALL

Video wall with resolution of 66.3MP for information and science visualization, one of the most advanced tools for scientific research in Latin America.

HCI FOR VIDEOWALL INTERACTION [Video]

Develop of human-computer interfaces to facilitate video wall usage, were implemented server-client applications using communication protocols like TUIO and VRPN to allow the control of the video wall using devices including smartphones, joystick, Myo gyroscope.

AUGMENTED-REALITY IMMERSION [Video]

Application to be displayed in video wall to generate immersive scenarios with Unity using perspective adjustment from a webcam streaming placed in the top of the videowall room.